Guide to the Israel Gerber Papers, 1920-2009 and undated RL.10184
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Israel Gerber papers
1920-2009 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina
Gerber, Israel J.
RL.10184
13.5 Linear Feet
Rabbi Israel Gerber was a Reform Rabbi and led congregations in Dothan, Alabama, North Carolina, and in Virginia. He served in the U.S. Army and held a PhD from Boston University in the Psychology of Religion. He authored six books and wrote numerous newspaper and magazine articles, including book reviews for the Charlotte Observer. Gerber was a sought-after lecturer because of his extensive biblical knowledge. The Israel Gerber Papers span the years 1920 to 2009 and primarily document public Gerber’s life, with the bulk of the materials related to his sermons, writings, and teachings. Also included is a small amount of correspondence, including letters to and from Harry Golden and letters to the editors of various newspapers, and two scrapbooks that document Gerber’s personal and professional life.
Provenance
The Israel Gerber Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina in June 2014.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Collection Overview
The Israel Gerber Papers span the years 1920 to 2009 and primarily document public Gerber’s life, with the bulk of the materials related to his sermons, writings, and teachings. Items in this collection include sermons on a variety of topics including Purim, Passover, World War II, and Genesis; various handwritten notes, typed speeches, lectures, eulogies, and talks given by Gerber at Temple Beth El and other temples, conferences, and academic institutions; and clippings, both loose and glued into scrapbooks related to Gerber’s books, and quotations, poems, articles, editorials written by Gerber and others on a variety of religious, spiritual, and inspirational topics, including Gerber’s monthly column “The Good Within Us” for Senior Directions.
Also included are teaching materials such as handwritten notes, lessons, quizzes and exams, a small amount of correspondence, including letters to and from Harry Golden and letters to the editors of various newspapers, and two scrapbooks that document Gerber’s personal and professional life. The scrapbooks include newspaper clippings, articles written by Gerber, letters, programs for various services and events, and invitations.
Historical note
Rabbi Israel Gerber (1918-2011) was a Reform Rabbi and led congregations in Dothan, Alabama, North Carolina (Temple Beth El, Charlotte [1959-1972] and then Temple Israel, Charlotte [1972-1974]), and in Virginia. Gerber served in the U.S. Army and held a PhD from Boston University in the Psychology of Religion. He authored six books, including The Psychology of the Suffering Mind and Man on a Pendulum, and wrote numerous newspaper and magazine articles, including book reviews for the Charlotte Observer. Gerber was a sought-after lecturer because of his extensive biblical knowledge.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are arranged chronologically.
Jews -- North Carolina; Rabbis -- North Carolina; Judaism, Reform; Judaism; Jewish sermons, American; Jewish sermons; North Carolina-Religion; Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina; Gerber, Israel J.
- Israel Gerber papers, 1920-2009 and undated
  - [Sermons - Genesis], 1920, 1943-2002; 1 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Sermons - Genesis], 1920, 1943-2002; 2 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Sermons - Genesis], 1920, 1943-2002; 3 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Sermons - Genesis], 1920, 1943-2002; 4 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1959 (Box 2)
  - Chanukah, 1940-1994; 1 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chanukah, 1940-1994; 2 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chanukah, 1940-1994; 3 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memorial Day, 1941-1965, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Passover, 1941-1990; 1 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Passover, 1941-1990; 2 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Passover, 1941-1990; 3 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - War Sermons, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sermons - How To, 1943-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interfaith Sermons & Talks, 1943-1993; 1 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Interfaith Sermons & Talks, 1943-1993; 2 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Interfaith Sermons & Talks, 1943-1993; 3 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Eulogies, 1943-2004; 1 of 6 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Eulogies, 1943-2004; 2 of 6 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Eulogies, 1943-2004; 3 of 6 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Eulogies, 1943-2004; 4 of 6 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Eulogies, 1943-2004; 5 of 6 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Eulogies, 1943-2004; 6 of 6 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Exodus, 1943-2004; 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Exodus, 1943-2004; 2 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Exodus, 1943-2004; 3 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sermons - Passover, 1943-2004; 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sermons - Passover, 1943-2004; 2 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sermons - Passover, 1943-2004; 3 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sermons - [Purim], 1943-2004; 1 of 4 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sermons - [Purim], 1943-2004; 2 of 4 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sermons - [Purim], 1943-2004; 3 of 4 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Sermons - [Purim], 1943-2004; 4 of 4 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - [Miscellaneous writings], 1944-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sermons - Chanukah, 1944-2003; 1 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sermons - Chanukah, 1944-2003; 2 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sermons - Chanukah, 1944-2003; 3 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Jewish War Veterans, 1945, 1963-1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Mother's Day, 1945-1966, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Love, 1945-1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sermons - Bar Mitzvah, 1945-2001; 1 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sermons - Bar Mitzvah, 1945-2001; 2 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Sermons - Bar Mitzvah, 1945-2001; 3 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sermons - Israel, 1946-2003; 1 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Sermons - Israel, 1946-2003; 2 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Sermons - Israel, 1946-2003; 3 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Genesis, 1947-1991 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - [Reader's responses to Gerber's articles in The Reconstructionist], 1948 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - The Reconstructionist contains "Pastoral Clinical Training in Operation", 1948 March (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - The Reconstructionist contains "A Rabbi 'in White'", 1948 March (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Confirmation Sermons, 1948, 1965-1982 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Confirmation Programs, 1948-1981, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Israel, 1948-1986; 1 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Israel, 1948-1986; 2 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Grief, 1949, 1962-1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Passover & Easter, 1949, 1965-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Reconstructionist contains "Religious Literature for the Physically Ill", 1950 January (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sermons - Labor, 1950-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - [Scrapbook - book reviews], 1950-1967 and undated; 1 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - [Scrapbook - book reviews], 1950-1967 and undated; 2 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Sermons - Design for Living, 1952-1954, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Palestinians, 1952, 1970-1985 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Humor, 1952, 1975-1979, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - American Judaism contains "Artie Shaw Finally Comes Home", 1953 January (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Jerusalem, 1953-1984; 1 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Jerusalem, 1953-1984; 2 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - [Letter - Hebrew Union College], 1954 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - [Gerber Editorials, Articles and Letters to the Editors], 1954-1999; 1 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - [Gerber Editorials, Articles and Letters to the Editors], 1954-1999; 2 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Offprint: A Rabbi Asks Concerning the Advisability of Informing Patients of the Seriousness of His Illness, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - [Record - Yeshiva University], 1955 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - [Miscellaneous], 1955, 1960-1961 and undated; 1 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - [Miscellaneous], 1955, 1960-1961 and undated; 2 of 2 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Lag B'omer, 1955-1957, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Book Reviews, 1956-1978 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - The Reconstructionist contains "Comprehensive but Not Convincing", 1957 March (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Message of Israel, 1957-1969 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Sermons - Charlotte, 1957-1979; 1 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sermons - Charlotte, 1957-1979; 2 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Israel & Christianity, 1957-1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Benedictions, Invocations, Prayers, 1958-1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Golden, Harry, 1959-1972; 1 of 3 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Golden, Harry, 1959-1972; 2 of 3 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Golden, Harry, 1959-1972; 3 of 3 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1973 (Box 7)
  - Jewish Heritage contains "Do Jews Commit Suicide?", 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - [Miscellaneous], 1960-1961, 1972 and undated; 1 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - [Miscellaneous], 1960-1961, 1972 and undated; 2 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Quotations, 1960-1983; 1 of 4 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Quotations, 1960-1983; 2 of 4 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Quotations, 1960-1983; 3 of 4 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Quotations, 1960-1983; 4 of 4 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - "Meditation on the High Holy Days" removed from The American Jewish Times-Outlook, 1961 September (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - The American Rabbi contains "Drawing Sermons from Experience", 1961 September (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Sermons - Leviticus, 1961-2003; 1 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Sermons - Leviticus, 1961-2003; 2 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - The American Rabbi contains "The Rabbi and the Counseling Field", 1962 February (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - [Miscellaneous writings], 1962-1967; 1 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - [Miscellaneous writings], 1962-1967; 2 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Sermons - Deuteronomy, 1962-2001 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Jewish Heritage contains "The Meaning of Freedom/Some Biblical Antecedents", 1964 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Archetype, 1965 and undated; 1 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Archetype, 1965 and undated; 2 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - The Christian Century contains "Pluralism and Public Prayer, Reiteration, and Reply to Replies", 1967 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - The Christian Century contains "God is Not Enough?", 1967 May (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Conversion, 1967-1994; 1 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Conversion, 1967-1994; 2 of 2 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Herencia Judia contains "El Significado de la Libertad", 1968 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - General, 1968, 1980-2003 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Holocaust, 1969-1996 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - [The Prophets], 1970, 1973 and undated; 1 of 4 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - [The Prophets], 1970, 1973 and undated; 1 of 4 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - [The Prophets], 1970, 1973 and undated; 3 of 4 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - [The Prophets], 1970, 1973 and undated; 4 of 4 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Sermons - Ethics of Fathers, 1970, 1982 and undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - [Talks and Lectures], 1970-1979 and undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - North Carolina Association of Jewish Woman Golden Anniversary contains "The Circuit Riding Rabbi Project", 1971 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - [Black Jews in Israel], 1971-1987 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Early Hebrew Religion, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Jewish Heritage contains "Circuit-Riding Rabbi", 1974 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Reconstructionist contains "The Jews of Rhodesia", 1977 March (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - The American Jewish Times Outlook contains "A Chanukah Message", 1981 December (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Sermons - Numbers, 1985-2003 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - [Miscellaneous], 1994-1995 and undated; 1 of 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - [Miscellaneous], 1994-1995 and undated; 2 of 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - [Letter - Department of Navy Chaplain Corps], 1999 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - [Handwritten notes], undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - [Handwritten notes - Mishnah], undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - [Handwritten notes - the Prophets], undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - [Lessons - The Torah and Bible Study], undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - O.T. [Old Testament], undated; 1 of 2 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - O.T. [Old Testament], undated; 2 of 2 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - [Scrapbook - clippings], undated; 1 of 3 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - [Scrapbook - clippings], undated; 2 of 3 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - [Scrapbook - clippings], undated; 3 of 3 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - [Scrapbook - Quotations], undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - [The Good Within Us], 1989-2009 (Box 9, Folder 14)